Guide to the Alexander Lmanian, Photographs of Washington, D.C., and New Haven, Connecticut
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Photographs of Washington, D.C., and New Haven, Connecticut.
1964-1969
1968-1969
GEN MSS 590
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.75
(2 boxes)
Photographs created by Alexander Lmanian that document locations and events in Washington, D.C., and its vicinity, 1964-1968, as well as New Haven, Connecticut, 1968-1969. The images of Washington document the physical impact of riots on the city following the assassination of Martin Luther King, Jr., April 4-8, 1968.
745 negatives: film, b & w; 5.7 x 5.7 cm. and smaller.
Lmanian, Alexander, 1925-1996
General note
Title devised by cataloger.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the William Reese Co. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile in box 1 may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital surrogates for all of the images in this collection are available through Digital Images Online database of the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Biography
Alexander Lmanian (1925-1996) was a sergeant in the United States Army in World War II, and after the war became a stringer photographer for the New Haven Register newspaper and the Associated Press.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of photographs created by Alexander Lmanian that document locations and events in Washington, D.C., and its vicinity, 1964-1968, as well as New Haven, Connecticut, 1968-1969.
Images of Washington document the physical impact of riots on the city following the assassination of Martin Luther King, Jr., April 4-8, 1968, as well as events and memorials in the city and vicinity, 1967-1968. Other images include figure and nude studies.
Images of New Haven primarily document locations in the city, including overhead views of the New Haven Green and city streets, particularly the intersection of Chapel Street and College Street, as well as images of the Yale University campus.
Many images show the interior of his rooms in Washington and New Haven, including his model airplanes, copy photographs of his calendar, and self-portraits.
Arrangement
Series I. Negatives
Riots -- Washington (D.C.) -- Pictorial works; New Haven (Conn.) -- Pictorial works; New Haven Green (New Haven, Conn.) -- Pictorial works; Washington (D.C.) -- Pictorial works; Washington (D.C.) -- 20th Century -- Pictorial works; Negatives (photographs); Lmanian, Alexander, 1925-1996; Yale University -- Pictorial works
- Negatives, 1964, 1967 December - 1968 November; Series I; (470 negatives)
  Scope and Contents
  All images depict locations and events in Washington, District of Columbia, except where noted.
  Arrangement
  Negatives are arranged in the original order of the negative book.
  General note
  All negatives are 120 millimeter strips, except where noted, four negatives per strip.
  Sleeve numbers 1-99 correspond to their original housing in the glassine sleeves of the negative book.
  Strips for 120 millimeter negatives are housed one to a sleeve, some groups of 35 millimeter negative strips are housed in the same sleeve to retain the orginal numbering scheme of the negative book.
  Dates for images are taken from inscriptions on the negative strips per a note in the collection by Lmanian. Other dates are derived from inscriptions on the glassine sleeves.
  - Negatives from Negative Sleeve Book
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 1 (negatives): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies available. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Theodore Roosevelt Island National Memorial, including a statue of Theodore Roosevelt sculpted by Paul Manship, 1968 April 28; (20 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    - John Ericsson National Memorial, located at Ohio Drive and Independence Avenue, SW, 1968 April 28; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Potomac River, 1968 April 28; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified, 1968 April 28; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Border of the District of Columbia and Maryland, 1968 April 28; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - United States Marine Corps War Memorial, 1968 March-April; (3 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - National Archives Building, Constitution Avenue, 1968 March-April; (12 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
    - United States Marine Corps War Memorial, 1968 March-April; (8 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
    - Arlington Cemetery and the Tomb of the Unknowns, Arlington, Virginia, 1968 March-April; (3 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Little girl playing at the Dupont Circle fountain at 12:30 p.m., 1964 May 17; (5 negatives (35 millimeter)) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Copy photograph of a map of and a tally of costs, 1968 April 13; (8 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
    - Landscapes and cityscapes, 1968 April 12; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - American Life Insurance Company of Baltimore, Maryland, and copy photographs of transparencies of a United States flag raising, 1968 April 12; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Cityscapes, 1968 April 12; (16 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 26-29)
    - Washington Monument, 1968 March 29; (8 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
    - Thomas Jefferson Memorial, 1968 March 29; (2 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - United States Army helicopter used to spot rioters, 1968 April 11; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Annotated calendar showing the month of April 1968, 1968 April 11; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Blossoming trees in spring, 1968 April 11; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Damage in the aftermath of the riots, 1968 April 7; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Luther Place Memorial Church, and cityscapes that show the aftermath of the riots, 1968 April 9; (8 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
    - Cityscapes in the aftermath of the riots, 1968 April 8; (8 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
    - Cityscapes during the riots in the vicinity of H Street NE between 7th Street NE and 13th Street NE, 1968 April 7; (12 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 41-43)
    - Self-portrait of Alexander Lmanian, and views of a statue and automobile, 1968 April 7; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Cityscapes during the riots, 1968 April 7; (24 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 45-50)
    - Police helicopters and emergency troops in the Capitol District during the riots, 11:00-11:30 a.m., 1968 April 6; (8 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 51-52)
    - Rioters, soldiers, and damaged buildings during the riots, 1968 April 5; (52 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 53-65)
    - National Sylvan Theater rehearsal for the crowning of the Cherry Blossom Princess from Michigan, and views of the Thomas Jefferson Memorial across the tidal basin, 1968 April 4; (8 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 66-67)
    - Views from out window of 336 2nd Street NE, 1968 April 4; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Japanese guests at the torch lighting for the National Cherry Blossom Festival, 1968 April 2; (8 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 69-70)
    - Army, Second Division Memorial near the Ellipse, 1968 April 2; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Washington Monument, 1968 April 2; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Fire at 12:25 PM in downtown, 1968 April 2; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Walter Edward Washington (1915-2003), Mayor-Commissioner of Washington, D.C., at a National Cherry Blossom Festival, 1968 April 2; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Japanese guests at the torch lighting for the National Cherry Blossom Festival, 1968 April 2; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Thomas Jefferson Memorial, 1968 March 27; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Tidal Basin and city streets, 1968 March 27; (8 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 77-78)
    - Annotated calendar showing the month of March 1968, and the interior of a room, 1968 March 23; (3 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Interior, possibly of a museum, 1968 February 25; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Interior, probably a museum and copy photograph of a receipt, 1968 February 25-27; (3 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Interior of a room with photography chemicals, including Mounted photographs lying on a bed with a flyer for the Chesapeake Bay Photography Contest, as well as an annotated calandar showing the month of October 1968, 1968 October 28; (5 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 82-83)
    - Construction of a subway railway on 3rd Street NW, between H Street NW and D Street NW, as well as copy photographs of an annotated calandar showing the month of February 1968, interiors of his room, and a self-portrait in a mirror, 1968 February 3; (30 negatives (35 millimeter)) (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Chinese New year celebrations, H Street NW, between 5th Street NW and 9th Street NW, 12:30-1:30 p.m., 1968 February 4; (70 negatives (35 millimeter)) (Box 1, Folder 85-86)
    - An informal portrait of Charles Edward Potter (1916-1979), former representative and senator of Michigan, as well as cityscapes, 1968 February 6; (6 negatives (35 millimeter)) (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Self-portrait of Alexander Lmanian and of his room, 1968; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Chinese New year celebrations, H Street NW, between 5th Street NW and 9th Street NW, 12:30-1:30 p.m., 1968 February 4; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Christmas tree and children, and a store display with children, 1967 December 24; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Nude and figure studies of a woman, 1968 March 21; (20 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 91-95)
    - Nude studies of a woman, 1968 March 7; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 96)
    - Nude studies of a woman, 1968 March 10; (8 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 97-98)
    - Nude studies of a woman, 1968 February; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - Little Traveler, studies of a young woman waiting for a bus in Alexandria, Virginia, 1968 March 10; (4 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Negative Sleeve Book
    - Negative sleeve book (Box 2)
  - Negatives from Loose Sleeves, 1968 September 11-1969 November 13; (275 negatives)
    Images that primarily document locations in New Haven, Connecticut, including overhead views of the New Haven Green and city streets, particularly the intersection of Chapel Street and College Street, as well as images of the Yale University campus. Many images show the interior of his room, including his model airplanes, copy photographs of his calendar, and self-portraits.
    Arranged chronologically.
    All negatives 120 millimeter strips with usually three or four negatives per strip.
    - Negatives, 1968 September 11-1969 November 13; (275 negatives) (Box 1, Folder 101-182)